<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties declaration, concerning his proceedings with his subjects of Scotland, since the pacification in the camp neere Berwick</title>
            <author>Windebank, Francis, Sir, 1582-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836850</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836850</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1270:23, 1291:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties declaration, concerning his proceedings with his subjects of Scotland, since the pacification in the camp neere Berwick</title>
                  <author>Windebank, Francis, Sir, 1582-1646.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 63, [1] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Young, His Majesties printer for Scotland, and R. Badger, printer to the prince His Highnesse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XL. [1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written for Charles I by Sir Francis Windebank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 22006 on UMI microfilm reel 1291.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears on reel 1270 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 1291 (Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1526-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History, (Charles I, 1625-1649) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:1140:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Charles I</figDesc>
                  <head>CHARLES BY THE GRACE OF GOD Kinge of England, Scotland France and Ireland, defendor of the faith, etc:</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1140:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HIS MAJESTIES Declaration, CONCERNING His Proceedings with His Subjects of SCOTLAND, Since the Pacification in the Camp neere <hi>Berwick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Young,</hi> His Majeſties Printer for <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <hi>R. Badger,</hi> Printer to the Prince His Highneſſe. M.DC.XL.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="blazon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1140:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1140:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>By the King.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E did make accompt that the Pacification which We were pleaſed to condeſcend unto, the laſt yeare in the Campe neere Berwick, and to grant to Our Subjects of Scotland, even then when they were in the height of their rebellion, and in the field in Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1140:3"/>Us, had given ſuch demonſtration to the world of Our inclination to peace, and deſire to ſpare the blood of Our people, and to winne them to the obedience which they owe unto Us, as that all miſunderſtandings had beene utterly taken away (as they were on Our part) and that ſuch conditions as were then agreed upon, ſhould have beene really performed by them, according to thoſe bonds of Allegeance, dutie, and promiſe in which they ſtand obliged to Us. But We have ſince found, to our unexpreſsible grief, that Our Princely goodneſſe and mildneſſe in paſsing by that offence, hath produced nothing but extreame ingratitude, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable inſolencies againſt Our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And farther, by ſundry libellous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, and moſt falſe and ſeditious diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſent from Scotland, and diſperſed purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this Our Kingdome of England, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in our Citie of London, that the cauſe of theſe diſorders is ſought to be ſhifted off from the Rebels in Scotland, and moſt unjuſtly caſt upon Us. Wherfore We hold Our ſelfe bound in that dutie which we owe to God and love to truth, not to ſuffer Our honour to be thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1140:3"/>and vilified by faction and rebellion, but to vindicate it from all calumnie and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, by giving hereby a cleare and juſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt to all the world of Our proceeding with Our Subjects of that Our Kingdome, and of the moſt materiall and remarkable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currents ſince that Pacification, that ſo all thoſe that are not partiall, or will not wilfully ſhut their eyes againſt the truth, may judge, who they are that have beene the diſturbers, and infractors of the peace, and that under the maske and viſour of Religion, ſeek to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine and ſubvert all Monarchicall and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Government. Which accompt followes thus.</p>
            <p>After We had beene ſome time in the Campe neere Berwicke, and that Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Scotland had encamped with their Armie in view of Ours, upon an overture from them, We were contented to conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the receiving of a Petition, in which it is expreſſed, that, <q>they, falling downe at Our feet, did moſt humbly ſupplicate Vs to appoint ſome of this Our Kingdome of England to heare, by ſome of them, their humble deſires.</q> Which We hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted, and ſeverall meetings by thoſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1140:4"/>of both Kingdomes having been held, at all which Our ſelf, (to ſhew Our hearty and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire to meet Our ſubjects in a peacable way) were contented to be preſent, (much beyond their own expectation, as they have ſince acknowledged, and We are ſure ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly beyond their merit) at the laſt thoſe of Scotland were commanded to make their demands in writing, in which after they had preſented their deſires, (of which one was, That the acts of the late aſſembly at Glaſgow holden by Our Indiction, might be ratified in the enſuing Parliament,) they profeſſe, <q>It is their griefe that We ſhould have beene provoked to wrath againſt them Our most humble and loving Subjects, and that it ſhall be their delight upon Our gracious aſſurance of the preſervation of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Lawes, to give example to others of all ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and temporall obedience which can be required or expected of loyall ſubjects.</q> Whereupon We letting them know, that for the better clearing of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, We expected from them the grounds &amp; reaſons of their deſires, but that We would not ſurpriſe them, and therefore gave them time to come prepared with their grounds in writing, The Lord <hi>Lowdon</hi> ſaid, <q>Their deſires
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1140:4"/>were onely to enjoy their Religion and Liberties, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and in clearing particulars, they would not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon any that were not ſuch.</q> This We willed him to ſet downe in writing under his hand, which he did in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Memorandum, that our deſires are onely the enjoying of our Religion and Liberties according to the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and Civill Lawes of His Majeſties Kingdome; To cleare by ſufficient Grounds, that the particulars which we humbly crave, are ſuch, and ſhall not inſiſt to crave any point which is not ſo warranted; And that we humbly offer all civill and temporall obedience to Your Majeſty, which can be required or expected of loyall ſubjects.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Signed, <hi>Lowdon.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To which We anſwered, That <q>if their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires were onely the enjoying of their Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties according to the Eccleſiasticall and Civill Lawes of Our Kingdome of Scotland, We do not onely agree to the ſame, but ſhall alwayes protect them to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of Our power. And if they ſhall not inſiſt upon any thing but that which is ſo warranted, We will moſt willingly and readily condeſcend unto it, ſo that in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1140:5"/>the meane time they pay unto Vs that civill and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obedience which can be juſtly required and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of loyall ſubjects.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This being the ground of the agreement on both ſides, We were pleaſed to proceed to a finall determination of this buſineſſe, which was brought to a concluſion upon the 17. of June, 1639: And Our Declaration of that date conformable to theſe grounds was thereupon made, which was not onely acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted by thoſe that came in the name of all thoſe of the Covenant, but moſt humble thankes were given to Us by them for Our gracious anſwer vouchſafed to their Petition in the ſaid Declaration; which was fully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, together with ſundry Articles, by all parties.</p>
            <p>The Pacification thus concluded, the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles on both ſides were to be performed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: Thoſe on Our part were in the Declaration following.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>We having conſidered the papers and humble petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons preſented to Vs by thoſe of Our ſubjects of Scotland who were admitted to attend Our pleaſure in the Camp, and after a full bearing by Our Selfe of all that they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1140:5"/>could ſay or alledge thereupon, having communicated the ſame to Our Councell of both Kingdomes there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, upon mature deliberation, with their unanimous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice We have thought fit to give this juſt and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous anſwer; That though We cannot condeſcend to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and approve the acts of the pretended Generall Aſſembly at Glaſgow, for many grave and weighty conſiderations which have happened both before and ſince, much importing the Honour and Security of that true Monarchicall Government lineally deſcended upon Vs from ſo many of Our Anceſtors; yet ſuch is Our gracious pleaſure, that notwithſtanding the many diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders committed of late, We are pleaſed not onely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and make good whatſoever our Commiſsioner hath granted and promiſed in Our Name; but alſo We are farther graciouſly pleaſed to declare and aſſure, that according to the Petitioners humble deſires, all matters Eccleſiaſticall ſhall be determined by the Aſſemblies of the Kirke, and matters Civill by the Parliament, and other inferiour Iudicatories eſtabliſhed by Law, which Aſſembly accordingly ſhalbe kept once a yeare, or as ſhalbe agreed upon at the Generall Aſſembly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And for ſetling the generall diſtractions of that Our ancient Kingdome, Our will and pleaſure is, that a free generall Aſſembly be kept at Edinburgh, the ſixt day of Auguſt next enſuing, where We intend (God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1140:6"/>willing) to be perſonally preſent; and for the Legall Indiction whereof, We have given order and command to Our Counſell, and thereafter a Parliament to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Edinburgh the twentieth day of Auguſt next en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, for ratifying of what ſhalbe concluded in the ſaid Aſſembly, and ſetling ſuch other things as may conduce to the peace and good of Our Native King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and therein an Act of oblivion to be paſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And whereas We are farther deſired, that Our Ships and Forces by land be recalled, and all perſons goods, and ſhips restored, and they made ſafe from invaſion, We are graciouſly pleaſed to declare, That upon their diſarming, and disbanding of their forces, diſſolving and diſcharging all their pretended Tables and Conventicles, and reſtoring unto us all our Caſtles, Forts, and Amunition of all ſorts, as likewiſe Our Royall Honours, and to every one of Our good ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects their liberties, lands, houſes, goods, and meanes whatſoever taken and detained from them ſince the late pretended Generall Aſſembly, We will preſently thereafter recall Our Fleet, and retire Our land Forces, and cauſe reſtitution to be made to all perſons of their ſhips and goods detained and arreſted ſince the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid time; whereby it may appeare, that Our intention of taking up of armes, was no way for invading of Our Native Kingdome, or to innovate the Religion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1140:6"/>and Lawes, but meerly for the maintaining and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating of Our Royall Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſince that hereby it doth cleerely appeare, that We neither have, nor do intend any alteration in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Lawes, but that both ſhalbe maintained by Vs in their full Integrity, We expect the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of that humble and dutifull obedience, which becommeth loyall and dutifull ſubjects, and as in their ſeverall Petitions they have often profeſſed. And as We have juſt reaſon to believe that to our peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and well-affected ſubjects this will be ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, ſo We take God and the world to witneſſe, that whatſoever calamities ſhall enſue by Our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitated ſuppreſsing of the Inſolencies of ſuch as ſhall continue in their diſobedient courſes, is not occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by Vs, but by their owne procurement.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Conditions in this Declaration that referre to the time paſt, have beene the moſt part of them already punctually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with by Us, that clauſe excepted in which We expreſſe, We intended to have beene at the Generall Aſſembly at Edin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh; which yet being but an Intention, We had aſſuredly performed, but that We were diverted by the diſorders committed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1140:7"/>by Our tumultuary Subjects in Edinburgh, upon the perſons of Our High Treaſurer, the Earle of Kinnoull Our Juſtice Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Sir <hi>Iames Hamilton,</hi> Counſellors of that Our Kingdome, and diverſe others Our good Subjects there; which gave Us juſt cauſe to ſuſpect, that there could be no ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for Our Perſon, among people inraged ſo immediately after Our clemency ſhewed to them in the Pacification.</p>
            <p>But one of the greateſt diſcouragements We had from going thither, was the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſuch Lords and others of that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom We ſent for, to come to Us to Berwick; by which diſobedience they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly diſcovered their diſtruſt of Us: and it cannot be thought reaſonable, that We ſhould truſt Our Perſon with thoſe that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted Us, after ſo many arguments and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of Our goodneſſe towards them.</p>
            <p>The Articles of Pacification agreed upon were theſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> The Forces of Scotland to be disbanded and diſſolved within forty eight houres, after the Publication of Our Declaration being agreed upon.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:1140:7"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Our Caſtles, Forts, Amunitions of all ſorts, and Royall Honours, to be delivered after the ſaid Publication, ſo ſoone as We ſhould ſend to receive them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Our Ships to depart preſently after the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Caſtles, with the firſt faire wind, and in the meane time no interruption of Trade or Fiſhing.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> We were graciouſly pleaſed to cauſe to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored all perſons goods and ſhips, detained and arrested ſince the firſt of November then laſt paſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> No Meetings, Treatings, Conſultations or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations of any Our Lieges, but ſuch as are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Act of Parliament.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> All Fortifications to deſiſt, and no farther working therein, and they to be remitted to Our Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> To reſtore to every one of Our good Subjects their liberties, lands, houſes, goods, and meanes whatſoever, taken or detained from them by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever meanes ſince the aforeſaid time.</p>
            </q>
            <p>On Tueſday the 18. of June, thoſe of Scotland came to Our Pavilion, and there We ſigned the aforeſaid Declaration, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1140:8"/>Articles were ſigned by them, who alſo ſigned another paper of ſubmiſſion to Us, as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>In the Camp, <date>18. June, 1639.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In obedience to His Majeſties Royall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, we ſhall upon Thurſday next, the</hi> 20. <hi>of this Iune, diſmiſſe our Forces, and immediately thereafter deliver His Majeſties Caſtles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and ſhall ever in all things carrie our ſelves like hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, loyall, and obedient ſubjects.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Signed,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rothes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dumfermlin.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Lowdon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Dowglas.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Alex. Henderſon.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>A. Iohnſtoun.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thoſe of Scotland did likewiſe further promiſe and undertake, that Our foreſaid Declaration ſhould be read and publiſhed in their Army; which was accordingly done by <hi>Lyon</hi> King of Armes of Scotland, on Thurſday the 20. in the preſence of the <hi>Earle of Morton, Sir Edmund Verney,</hi> and <hi>Sir Iohn Borough,</hi> Our Commiſsioners ſent thither to ſee the ſame performed.</p>
            <p>How theſe Articles have beene per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1140:8"/>on their part, comes now to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and will appeare by that which followes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, whereas We, by the publication of the Articles of Pacification, expected that due reſpect and acknowledgment of Our authority, which might have witneſſed their Loyalty, and ſenſe of their thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for ſo great and royall favour, We found on the contrary, that at the very pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it in their Camp, the ſame was met with a Proteſtation, ſo ſcandalous and diſhonourable to Our Government, as Our Subjects were thereby rather encouraged in their former mutinous wayes, than reduced to that obedience which they promiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, they delivered into the hands of ſome of Our Engliſh Nobility, and ſpred, among others, a ſcandalous Paper, intituled, <hi>Some Conditions of His Majeſties Treaty with His Subjects of Scotland before the Engliſh Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, are ſet down here for remembrance.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are contained ſuch untruths and ſeditious poſitions, and ſo contrary to that which was concluded in the Articles of Pacification, as thereby it did plainly appeare, that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1140:9"/>they pretended a deſire of peace, yet they intended nothing leſſe. This falſe and ſeditious paper comming to Our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was after, by the Advice, and upon the humble Petition of Our Privie Councell here in England, and particularly, by ſuch Noblemen as were pretended by them to be witneſſes to the ſame, ordered to be damned by Proclamation, and publikely burnt by the hand of the Hangman: which was done accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Thirdly, whereas it was promiſed, that the Forces of that Our Kingdome of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, raiſed without Our warrant, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Our Selfe, ſhould be disbanded and diſſolved within 48. hours after publication of Our ſaid Declaration in their Camp; they did nevertheleſſe for ſome time, keep in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diverſe Forces, and have ever ſince held in pay almoſt all their Officers, in manifeſt breach of thoſe Articles, contempt of Our Royall Authority, contrary to the Lawes of that Our Kingdome, and to the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of all Our Subjects, who did give obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Our Commandements there, which cleerely ſhewed their intention of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1140:9"/>putting themſelves againe in armes againſt Us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> Fourthly, Whereas it was promiſed, that Our Forts, Caſtles, and Amunitions, ſhould be reſtored, ſo ſoone as We ſhould ſend to receive them, yet full reſtitution was not made accordingly; And for the Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at Lieth, which was with the reſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Our pleaſure, it ſtands entirely as it did, though We often commanded the demoliſhing thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> Fifthly, It was promiſed there ſhould be no Meetings, Treatings, Tables, Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Convocations, or Conventicles, but ſuch as are warranted by act of Parliament, (and yet We were pleaſed to give them warrant to meet for the ſpace of one moneth, to conſult, adviſe, and reſolve, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch affaires and buſineſſe as concerned the reliefe of their mutuall burthens only:) Nevertheleſſe after that time expired, which was on the twentieth day of July 1639. they did, and doe ſtill continue their unlawfull meetings and conſultations upon matters of State both Eccleſiaſticall and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, contrary to the Laws and Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1140:10"/>of that Our Kingdome, and Our expreſſe warrant; In which Conventicles they daily vex and trouble ſuch of Our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as doe not adhere to their rebellious Covenant, and pretended aſſembly at Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gow, and the acts of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> Sixthly, Whereas all Fortifications were to be remitted to Our pleaſure to be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed or continued, and We having given commandement for the demoliſhing of them all raiſed and built without Our warrant; no obedience is given to the ſame, but they are ſtill continued, to the foſtering of ſedition among Our Subjects, and the diſturbance of the peace of that Our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> Seventhly, Whereas all Our good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects ſhould have their liberties and goods reſtored to them, yet ſuch is the violence and furie of the people, animated thereunto by the ſaid Proteſtation, ſcandalous papers ſpred, and ſeditious Sermons preached, as many of Our ſaid Subjects are deterred from going to their owne dwelling and places of aboad, and threatned with the loſſe of their lives, in caſe they ſhall repaire to their own houſes.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1140:10"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> Eightly, Whereas in Our Declaration before mentioned, We did make knowne that We could not approve the late preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded generall Aſſembly at Glaſgow, for the reaſons conteyned in Our former Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet contrary to that Our pleaſure, they daily preſſe Our Subjects to ſubſcribe the approbation of the ſaid pretended aſſembly and acts thereof, and to ſweare the ſame; ſo that whereas We did expect to have found our Subjects ſetled in peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe againſt Our repaire to Edinburgh, We heard of nothing but new diſorders, meetings and moleſtations of Our Subjects well affected to Our ſervice; which as it doth evidently appeare by the inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſolencies committed as aforeſaid, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the perſons of Our High Treaſurer the Earle of <hi>Kinnoul,</hi> Our Juſtice Generall Sir <hi>Iames Hamilton,</hi> and others Our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours and good Subjects, ſo doth it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evince, that nothing was leſſe intended then obedience to Our authoritie, or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what was promiſed, or is due to Us in right of Our Crowne, and by the lawes of that Our Kingdome.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1140:11"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> Ninthly, Whereas We were pleaſed to grant a free Generall Aſſembly, for ſetling and compoſing the diviſions cunningly rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and fomented in the Church of that Our Kingdome, expecting a faire choice of the Commiſsioners, and ſuch as might ſtand with the reſpect due to Our authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they did labour to pervert Our Subjects by anticipating their voices, in making them ſweare to, and ſubſcribe the acts of the pretended Aſſembly at Glaſgow, and making choiſe of ſuch Commiſsioners (and no others) as adhered thereunto, and by Oath were bound to maintaine the ſame, and further, deterred others, whom We by Our Warrant did lawfully call to the next Aſſembly, from repairing thereunto, threatning them with the loſſe of their lives, and what worſe may be committed againſt their perſons, in manifeſt contempt of Our authority, and derogation from the freedome of the ſaid aſſembly.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> Tenthly, To divert all Our good Subjects from their due obedience to Us, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch them to their factious mutinies and diſorders, they brand all ſuch as adhere to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1140:11"/>Us, and have attended Our perſon, with the vile aſperſion of Traitors to God and their Countrey, threatning to proceed againſt them with cenſures accordingly, as though the due reſpect given by them to Us, and their adhering to Us, and their aſsiſting Us in their perſons, were Treaſon: whereas by right of that Our Crown, and the Acts of Parliament of that Our Kingdome, all Our Subjects are to riſe with Us, and to aſsiſt Us with their bodies and goods, and whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever refuſes, or riſes in Armes or rebellion againſt Us, or commits any act of Hoſtility againſt Our Sacred Perſon, are declared Traitors, and are to incurre the paine of High Treaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XI"/> Laſtly, Their diſobedience appeares in that unparallel'd contempt of Our Royall authority, and ſhaking off all reſpect due to Sacred Majeſtie, by their proteſting that all members of the Colledge of Juſtice, and all Our Lieges were not to attend the Seſsion, and that all Acts, Decrees, and Sentences therein paſt againſt any of them, ſhall be nul, void and ineffectuall, contrary to Our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe warrant for the downeſitting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1140:12"/>and to the heavie dammage of Our good Subjects, who were thereby fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of Juſtice, taking by this meanes Our Royall Power out of Our hand, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone belongeth to Us, none but Our ſelfe being to command Our Subjects to attend the Seſsion, or to diſcharge their attendance, as We in Our Princely wiſdome and juſtice ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>Having laid theſe inſolent and ſeditious foundations for a Parliament, it could not in reaſon be expected but the ſtructure to be raiſed thereupon muſt be full of diſorder and confuſion, and indeed it prooved all of a piece, for in all the progreſſe of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament their actions and demands were full of undutifulneſſe and diſloyaltie, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Us the moſt eſſentiall, and inherent prerogatives of Our Crowne, and ſtriving by all meanes to change and alter the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Parliament, and frame of Government, as appeares by their firſt Act, at and after the chuſing of the Lords of the Articles, where, in a moſt inſolent and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory way, they proteſted, that nothing done, or to be done in Parliament ſhould
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1140:12"/>be valid, except the forme of electing the Articles heretofore obſerved were altered, every Eſtate allowed to chooſe their owne Articles, contrary to the forme kept in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Parliaments for many yeares, as will cleerely be evinced by the Records, and will be made appeare by perſons of all qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities yet living, who aſsiſted at the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and were members of the ſame, in the Yeare 1612. and 1609. and contrary to the proviſions and conditions mentioned in the Act, 1587.</p>
            <p>By their Act likewiſe concerning the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining of the power of the ſaid Articles, they preſſe totally to ſubvert the frame and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer therof. The Articles have been, as is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by themſelvs, ever ſince K. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Bruce</hi> his time, which is about 300. years; and by the Lords of the Articles all buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are prepared, and from them brought to the Parliament, as appeares by divers Acts of Parliament, and particularly by the fourth Parliament of K. <hi>Iames</hi> 6. Cap. 218. in which for eſchewing of confuſion and impertinent motions, all Propoſitions to be made in Parliament are to be delivered to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1140:13"/>the Clerk Regiſter, and by him preſented to the Lords of the Articles, that all frivolous and improper motions may be rejected; which ancient Conſtitutions they would ſubvert by the aforeſaid Act.</p>
            <p>So by the Act concerning the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Parliament in time to come, they urge, and thereby ſtrive totally to alter the frame of the Parliament, and to confound and take away the third Eſtate, wherein the Civill power of Kings is ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, as Our Father, and all His Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in former Parliaments, both in time of Popery, and ſince the reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have beene moſt carefull to preſerve and maintaine the Dignity, Honour, and Priviledges of the third Eſtate, as appeares in <hi>Anno</hi> 1560. when all Church-Juriſdiction in the perſons of Biſhops, is alledged to be aboliſhed: and in <hi>Anno</hi> 1587. when all the Temporalties of Benefices were annexed to the Crowne, the Clergy retained ſtill their Vote in Parliament, and repreſented the third Eſtate, and the Civill power and priviledges of the Church were ſtill preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and againe ratified, as appeares by the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1140:13"/>firſt Parliament of K. JAMES 6. <hi>Cap.</hi> 24. and by diverſe Acts of Parliament, <hi>Anno</hi> 1587. 1597. &amp; 1609. By all which, and diverſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acts of Parliament, it does cleerely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, how much the Kings Our Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors have conceived their Civill Power, and the Honour of their Crowne to be concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the maintaining and upholding of the Honour, Dignity and Priviledges of the three Eſtates. Nay, by a ſpeciall Act made in the time of K. JAMES 6. Parliament 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 130. it is declared Treaſon, to impugne the authority of the Parliament, and three Eſtates, or to procure the innovation of the power and authority of the ſame three Eſtates, or any of them: and We would willingly know, how they, or any of them, can deny, but that they have ſought the breach of this Act, and ſo are guilty of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and liable to the puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Act which they call Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſſory, they do not onely thereby ſeeke to take away the third Eſtate, which is Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as aforeſaid, but to annull many other Acts, formerly made in favour of the Crowne; and farther, to barre Us, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1140:14"/>totally, from Aſſembly, or Aſſembly bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and cut Us off from all thoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Civill affaires, which in the Court of that Kingdome, are in conſequence hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; by which it is evident, how farre they would trench upon Regall power, and how different it is from their promiſe, which was, to deſire nothing that is not warranted by Law.</p>
            <p>For the Act of Oblivion, in the narrative and whole ſtreyne of it, as it is formed, and deſired by them to be paſt in Parliament, they ſeeke to juſtifie themſelves in all their proceedings, and inſtead of an Act of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, for which they petitioned Us at the Campe, they urge an Act which amounts to a Juſtification to be recorded in the Bookes of Parliament, altogether contrary to the nature of an Act of Oblivion, and to that which ever heretofore hath been deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in like caſe, as appeares by the Act of Oblivion in <hi>Anno</hi> 1563.</p>
            <p>And whereas by the Act of Pacification, reſtitution is ordained to be made to every one of Our good Subjects of their liberties, lands, goods and meanes whatſoever, taken
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1140:14"/>and detained from them by any meanes, ſince the aforeſaid time, this is not onely not yet performed, but as appeares by the bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part of this Act, it is never intended.</p>
            <p>And as by the aboveſaid act of Oblivion, ſo by their Act of Reliefe, they depart from that which was condeſcended to at the Campe; for whereas upon their humble deſire We were graciouſly pleaſed by a Commiſsion dated at Berwick 2. of July 1639. to allow them the libertie of convening and meeting untill a certaine day, for diſtributing of their pretended charges, amongſt ſuch as ſhould willingly condeſcend thereunto, they have not only without Our warrant kept their Conventicles, and Tables, ſince the expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the aforeſaid Commiſsion, contrary to the poſitive lawes of the Kingdome, and the Act of Pacification, and their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement in petitioning for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Commiſsion, but by their ſaid Act of reliefe they doe moſt impudently urge upon Us, that by an Act of Our Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Power, all Our good Subjects who in the late troubles and Commotions did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to Us, and ſhew themſelves ready to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1140:15"/>defend Our Royall Authority, ſhould bee made equally, if not more lyable to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraying of their pretended charges. So by the Act it ſelfe. We are preſſed to juſtifie and authoriſe all their Rebellions and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and to conſtraine the innocent and thoſe that have ſuffered moſt for being faithfull and loyall to Us, to contribute to thoſe Rebellions and Treaſons; then which there can be nothing more Tyrannicall, nor contrary to Juſtice and Our Honour.</p>
            <p>Concerning their demands, although in all their Petitions, Declarations and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances, they profeſſe, that they will never incroach upon Soveraigntie, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh Our Royall Authority, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by their demands made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the reaſons of them given to Our ſelfe, they ſtrike at the very roote of Our Regall power. For they deſire,</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> Firſt, that the Coyne be not medled with but by advice of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> That no ſtranger be entruſted with keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Our Caſtles, nor other perſon put in them, but by advice of the Eſtates.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> That no Patent of Honour be granted to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1140:15"/>any ſtranger, but ſuch as have a competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of land-rent in Scotland.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IV"/> That no Commiſsion of Juſticiary or Lieutenancie may be granted but for a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted time. </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> They proteſt likewiſe againſt the Prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie of Our Lord Treaſurer, and Lord Privie Seal, becauſe as they alledge the ſame is not warranted by a poſitive Law.</p>
            <p>All which, though they are ſo eſſentially belonging to Us as their King, that for the moſt part they anſwer themſelves; yet We have thought it not unfit to give the world this ſatisfaction concerning them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> And firſt for the Coine, It is a preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive moſt peculiar to the Crowne, and none can meddle with it but by Our conſent, without incurring the puniſhment of High Treaſon, as it is in all Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I. II."/> In the ſecond and third there lurketh a great deale of Malignity and Poyſon, and they are intended meerely againſt the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, whom they would accompt ſtrangers, as appeares by the exception lately taken by thoſe of Edinburgh to thoſe Engliſh ſent by Us to the Caſtles of Edinburgh and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1140:16"/>Downebarton. This is a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſeditious practice, to raiſe againe the partition wall betweene the two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and to divide them, thereby to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thoſe ancient Nationall animoſities, which have beene moſt happily laid aſleep by the bleſſed union of the two Crownes; And beſides, the great diſhonour to the Engliſh, that they ſhould not be held wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to enjoy any dignities or priviledges in Scotland, as well as the Scots doe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: It is an injurie to themſelves, For it is moſt juſt, that by the ſame rule the Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati of Scotland (who are now admitted here to all Dignities, Priviledges and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and doe enjoy them as freely as any Engliſh whatſoever) ſhould be likewiſe excluded from them, for which moſt of their Countreymen here would give them little thankes. But what Religion there can be in ſhewing themſelves ſuch Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaries, We leave it to the world to judge.</p>
            <p>To the fourth: Some of themſelves have obtained from Us the heritable Rights of Juſticiary, over a conſiderable part of that Our Kingdome, and why Our power
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1140:16"/>ſhould be more limitted to others then to them We underſtand not.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> To the fifth: No man that is not a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor can deny that the ſource and fountaine of all honour is in Us, and that it is a prime branch of Our Crowne to diſtribute ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Dignities, and precedeneies to whom We pleaſe, and beſides, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of that Our Kingdome, holds his place and precedency without any warrant or poſitive law, but meerely from Our immediate and inherent power; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why not Our Treaſurer and Privie Seale, as well as He?</p>
            <p>They further boldly demand the reſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Acts of Parliament concerning the Civill government, namely, the Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Judicatorie of the Exchequer, the Act concerning Proxies, the Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning confirmation of Ward-lands, by which they would overthrow both Our Government and Revenew.</p>
            <p>When We found them thus pertinaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved to perſiſt in theſe their inſolent and unſufferable demands, contrary to all Religion and Lawes, though they ſo much
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1140:17"/>pretend them both, We ſignified Our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to Our Commiſsioner the Earle of Traquair to this purpoſe, That whereas it did evidently appeare unto Us, that the aime of divers of Our Subjects was not now for Religion, as they have alwayes pretended (for it was manifeſt by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of Our ſaid Commiſsioner, how willing We had beene to give ſatisfaction both in Aſſembly and Parliament, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all ſuch things as were promiſed by Us, or ſued for by them under that name of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) And that We did perceive by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny new ſtrange Propoſitions, that nothing would give them content but the alteration of the whole frame of the Government of that Kingdome, and withall, the totall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of Royall Authority, We held it muſt now be Our care and endeavour to prevent that which did ſo neerely concerne Us in ſafety and Honour, and if thereupon we ſhould immediately command the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving of the Parliament, it were no more then juſtly might be expected from Us. Nevertheleſſe, ſuch was ſtill Our tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their preſervation, and of the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1140:17"/>of a perfect peace in that Our native Kingdome, as We were pleaſed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to prorogate the ſame, and to heare ſuch reaſons as they could give for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Wherfore We commanded Our ſaid Commiſsioner to prorogate the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment untill the 2. of June next enſuing, and that (ſince they had diſputed it) by Our au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority only; We holding it no way fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that any aſſent of theirs but obedience ſhould be had to that act, which doth ſo properly belong to Us as their King, and if they ſhould preſume to proteſt, ſit ſtill, and diſobey this our Royall command, Our further will and pleaſure was, that Our ſaid Commiſsioner ſhould diſcharge their ſo doing under paine of Treaſon. But in caſe of their obedience and diſſolving according to Our command, then We did require Our ſaid Commiſsioner to declare unto them, that We would not only admit to Our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſuch as they ſhould ſend unto Us to repreſent their deſires, and the reaſons of them, but would likewiſe, as We were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready to do, punctually perform what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. We did promiſe. In the interim We
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1140:18"/>commanded himſelfe with all convenient ſpeed to repaire hither, and to bring with him all that had paſſed, or had been deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, both in Aſſembly and Parliament, that ſo we might not only be more perfectly inform'd of all proceedings, but likewiſe conſult with him and thoſe of our Councel, what courſe would be beſt for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Our honour, and the happy accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation of this buſines.</p>
            <p>This Our command being ſignified to the Parliament by Our Commiſsioner, was not aſſented unto without a Proteſtation, which they call a Declaration of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this purpoſe. That</p>
            <q>
               <p>Whereas <hi>John</hi> Earle of <hi>Traquair</hi> His Majeſties Commiſsioner, honoured with a moſt ample Commiſsion, according to His Majeſties Royall word having cloſed the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and ſitting in Parliament with them a very long time for debating and preparing ſuch Articles as were to be repreſented in face of Parliament, did now take upon him, and that without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Eſtates and without any offence on their part, who have endeavoured in all their proceedings to witnes their loyalty to the King, and duty to His Grace, as repreſenting His Majeſties ſacred perſon
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1140:18"/>to prorogate the Parliament upon a private warrant procured by ſiniſter information againſt His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties publicke Patent under the Great Seale, &amp;c. whereby hee heavily offends all His Majeſties good Subjects, and endeangers the peace of the whole kingdome, for which he must be lyable to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties animadverſion, and to the cenſure of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this being a new and unuſuall way, without preſident in this Kingdome, contrary to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties honour ſo farre engaged for preſent ratifying the Acts of the Kirke, contrary to the lawes, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and perpetuall practice of the Kingdome, by which all continuations of Parliament once called, convened, and begun to ſit, have ever been made with expreſſe conſent of the Eſtates, as may be ſeen in the Reignes of ſundry Princes, &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Jac. 6. Qu. Mary. Jac. 5. Jac. 4. Jac. 3. Jac. 2. &amp; Jac. 1.</note> Therefore wee the Eſtates of Parliament, &amp;c. are conſtrained in this extremitie to manifeſt and declare, &amp;c. that as wee have not given the leaſt cauſe or ſmalleſt occaſion of this unexpected, or unexemplified Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation; ſo wee judge and know the ſame to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the conſtitution and practices of all prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Parliaments, contrary to the liberties of this free and ancient Kingdome, and very repugnant to His Majeſties Royall intentions, promiſe, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious expreſsions in the Articles of the late Pacificà<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1140:19"/>&amp;c. And wee doe further declare, that any Prorogation made by the Commiſsioners Grace alone, without conſent of the Parliament, by himſelfe or any Commiſsioner in his name, under the Quarter Seale, or by the Lords of the Councell, who have no power at all in matters of the Parliament during the ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof, ſhall be ineffectuall and of no force at all to hinder the lawfull proceedings of the Subjects, and the doers thereof to be cenſurable in Parliament. And further wee declare, that the Commiſsioner his nomination of the Articles by himſelfe, his calling together thoſe Articles, and commanding them to ſit continually and proceed, notwithſtanding their daily Proteſtations to the contrary; his keeping frequent ſeſsions of Councell, and determining cauſes in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell during the time of ſeſsion in Parliament; his calling downe and calling up of money during the ſeſsion of Parliament, without conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, notwithstanding the Parliament had taken the money to their conſideration, and had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have given their advice for a determination thereanent; his frequent prorogating of the riding of the Parliament, without conſent of the Estates, or mentioning in the Acts of Prorogation, the conſent of the Articles, although it were done by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, are contrary to the liberties of the Kingdome,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1140:19"/>freedome and cuſtome of Parliament; and that they be no preparatives, practiques, nor prejudices in time comming againſt us, or our ſucceſſors. But becauſe we know that the eyes of the world are upon us, that Declarations have been made and publiſhed againſt us, &amp;c. that our proceedings may be made odious to ſuch as know not the way how theſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are procured from His Majeſtie, nor how they are made knowne nor intimate to us, and doe as little conſider that wee are not private Subjects, but a ſitting Parliament; or what nationall prejudices we have ſuſtained in time paſt by miſ-information, and what is the preſent caſe of the Kingdome; We there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declare, that whatſoever by the example of our predeceſſours in like caſes of neceſsity, by His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Indiction, and by the Articles of Pacification wee might doe lawfully in ſitting ſtill, and which in this extreme neceſsity were juſtifiable not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo juſt a King, but to the faces of our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; yet out of our moſt reverend regard, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſire, to render not onely all reall demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of civill obedience, but to put farre from us all ſhew or appearance of what may give His Majeſtie the leaſt diſcontent, wee have reſolved for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent onely to make remonſtrance to His Majeſtie of the reaſon of our propoſitions and proceedings in this
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1140:20"/>Parliament, &amp;c. and in expectation of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties gracious anſwer to theſe our humble Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances, ſome of each Eſtate having power from the whole body of the Parliament, remaine ſtill here at Edinburgh, to attend the returne of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties gracious anſwer to our humble and juſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands: and further to remonſtrate our humble deſires to His Majeſtie upon all occaſions, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it may be made moſt manifeſt againſt all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that it was never our intention to deny His Majeſtie any part of that civill and temporall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience which is due to all Kings from their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and from us to our dread Soveraigne after a more eſpeciall manner, but meerly to preſerve our Religion and Liberties of the Kingdome, without which Religion cannot continue long in ſafety: And if it ſhall happen (which God forbid) that after wee have made our Remonſtrances, and to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of our power and duty uſed all lawfull meanes for His Majeſties Information, that our malicious enemies, who are not conſiderable, ſhall by their ſuggeſtions and lyes prevaile againſt Informations, and generall Declarations of a whole Kingdome, we take God and men to witneſſe, that wee are free of the outrages and inſolences that may be committed in the meane time, and that it ſhall be to us no impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1140:20"/>that we are conſtrained to take ſuch courſe as may beſt ſecure the Kirke and Kingdome from the extremity of confuſion and miſery: Which Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above written, wee the Eſtates of Parliament required the Clerke to inſert in the records thereof, and grant extracts thereof under his hand and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
               <p>This Declaration was produced and read in the outer houſe of Parliament, upon <hi>Decemb.</hi> 18. 1639. according whereunto the Nobility nominated and appointed the Earles of Lothian, and Dalhouſe, the Lords Yeſter, Balmerino, Cranſton, and Naper: The Barons nominated the Commiſsioners of the three, Lothians, Fife, and Tweddell: The Burroughes nominated the Commiſsioners of Edinburgh, Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lithgow, Sterline, Hadington, Dunbarre, to attend at Edinburgh the returne of His Majeſties gracious anſwer to their humble Remonſtrances.</p>
            </q>
            <p>In this Proteſtation or Declaration, though there be a ſpecious ſhew, and ſundry profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of obedience to Us, yet it is evident they have wounded Our Authority in the perſon of the Earle of Traquair Our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioner, who did nothing in that Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation but by Our ſpeciall commandement;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1140:21"/>and therefore for that they cannot cenſure Him, without reflection upon Us; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it is poſitively affirmed, that <q>any Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation made by the Commiſsioner alone, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Parliament, ſhall be ineffectuall, and of no force,</q> which neceſſarily implies, that Wee have no power to prorogue, whereas the contrary is moſt manifeſt truth. And though upon Our command there was a ſhew of Prorogation, yet they continued part of their Body at Edinburgh, upon pretence of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Our anſwer to their Remonſtrance; which, if it ſhall not be to their liking, they conclude with a menacing Proteſtation, that <q>It ſhall be no imputation to them if they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to take ſuch courſe as may beſt ſecure the Kirke and Kingdome from the extremity of confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and miſery,</q> having firſt taken God and Men to witneſſe, <q>that they will be free of all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages and inſolencies that may bee committed in the meane time,</q> then which nothing can be more boldly and inſolently ſpoken.</p>
            <p>After this, theſe divided members of that diſtracted Parliamentary Body remaining thus at Edinburgh, did ſend the Earle of Dumfermlin, and the Lord Lowdon, as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1140:21"/>their Deputies, to make their Remonſtrance to Us; but becauſe We underſtood, that they came without warrant or licence from Our Commiſsioner, and had not acquainted Him with what they were to propound unto Us, We held this like the reſt, a great and inſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſobedience, and would not admit them to Our preſence comming in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and ſo commanded them to returne without hearing them.</p>
            <p>Then Our Commiſsioner came hither, and made a report to Us of the ſtate of Our affaires there, with which We thought fit to acquaint the Lords of Our Councell of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as alſo with this carriage of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Scotland, and to adviſe with them what was to bee done for redreſſe of theſe diſorders. Whereupon Wee commanded Our ſaid Commiſsioner the Earle of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quair, to make relation to the Boord of all their exorbitant demands, of which ſome accompt had been formerly given them by the Lord Marqueſſe Hamiltoun. Upon this Our command the Earle of Traquair made a large and exact repreſentation to the Boord of the moſt conſiderable matters propoſed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1140:22"/>and agitated in Parliament, and of the inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of their demands, and the Petitioners themſelves ſent from Scotland, have ſince their comming to Us inſiſted upon all and every particular of Our ſaid Commiſsioners relation, and in a moſt bold way offered to juſtifie them all, by which they have more then juſtified the report of the ſaid Earle of Traquair: Whereupon We were further plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to acquaint the Lords, that they had late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent Us a Petition, which carried ſome ſhew of ſubmiſsion and humility, but was indeed nothing leſſe, wherein they deſired, that ſome might be allowed to come from them to Us, to repreſent their affaires; which to make Our Subjects of Scotland the more inexcuſable, Wee todl the Lords Wee had granted, though Wee had little cauſe to hope for any good from thoſe that had ſo much forgotten their duty and allegeance to Us.</p>
            <p>When the Lords had heard the relation of Our Commiſsioner, Wee thought fit upon the whole matter to put this queſtion to them, Whether conſidering the inſolencie and height of theſe demands, even concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing civill obedience, it were not fit to reduce
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1140:22"/>them to their dutie by force, rather then to give way to theſe demands, ſo prejudiciall to Us in honour and ſafety. To this Wee commanded every one of Our Councell to give his anſwer, and to declare his opinion by vote; which was accordingly done, and they unanimouſly voted in the affirmative: whereupon ſoone after We reſolved to call a Parliament.</p>
            <p>After this, Our Subjects in Scotland, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the anſwer We gave them upon their Petition, having ſent up hither foure Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>viz.</hi> the Earle of Dumfermlin, the Lord Lowdon, Sir <hi>William Douglas,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Berkeley,</hi> We were pleaſed to admit them to Our preſence, and to receive Petitions from them, which were after by Our direction ſubſcribed by them; in one of which, they, in the name of the Aſſembly convened at Edinburgh, gave Us thankes for that Wee had made knowne to them, that all matters Eccleſiaſticall ſhould be determined in free nationall Aſſemblies, and matters Civill in Parliaments; and deſired Our ratification of the Conſtitutions of the Aſſembly, in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And in the other they deſired to bee
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1140:23"/>heard before Us, and ſome of Our Councell of both Kingdomes; and that the report made by the Earle of Traquair to Our Councell here in England, might be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in writing under his hand; which was a moſt inſolent demand.</p>
            <p>Immediately after this, Wee thought fit to appoint a ſpeciall Committee of ſome of Our Councell to heare them, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gave order to the Earle of Traquair to aſsigne them a day to come to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee. They refuſed to come, alledging that they had order and inſtructions to treat with none but Our Selfe: Whereupon Wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them to attend Us at the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, though it were the day of Our appointed remove to Hampton Court, at which time they did attend Us accordingly.</p>
            <p>There the Lord Lowdon made a long ſpeech, the effect whereof was, a Proteſtation of the independencie of the Parliament of Scotland, and that it is ſubject to no other Judicatory, a profeſsion of their loyaltie and affection to Us, and a juſtification of their proceedings in the Aſſembly and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as agreeable to the Articles of Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1140:23"/>and to the Lawes and Practices of that Kingdome; and thereupon a deſire that We would ratifie and confirme thoſe their proceedings, and to that purpoſe command that the Parliament might proceed freely for the determining of all the Articles delivered in to them, and the eſtabliſhing of Religion and Peace in the Kingdome, undertaking that whatſoever objections or informations ſhould be made againſt their proceedings in Parliament, if they might receive them in writing, they would make anſwer to them.</p>
            <p>This diſcourſe ended, Wee demanded what power and commiſsion they had to give Us ſatisfaction, and to oblige thoſe from whom they came, ſeeing if they had none, Wee ſhould heare them upon great diſadvantage, they expecting ſatisfaction from Us, who have power to give it, but they none to render the like to Us. They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that which they ſhould propoſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing agreeable to Law, they were confident would give Us ſatisfaction. We asked who ſhould be Judge of that; They anſwered the Lawes would be ſo cleere, that there ſhould
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1140:24"/>be no need of a Judge; and though We inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted much hereupon, they would give Us no other ſatisfaction; they avowing they had powers, and would bring them to Us: they were ordered to doe ſo at the next meeting, and ſo for that time were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed.</p>
            <p>After Our returne from Hampton Court, they attended Us at the Committee againe, where they produced Inſtructions, ſigned by ſome Scottiſh Lords, and others, perſons of no great eminencie; which Inſtructions having been read, were judged by Us (all the Committee concurring in the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) to be no commiſsion, nor that they had any power or authority by them to give Us ſatisfaction, or to oblige thoſe, from whom they ſaid they came, to any thing that Wee ſhould yeeld to, or deſire.</p>
            <p>Wherefore We demanding whether they had any other powers, they ſaid they had a paper formerly ſubſcribed by ſome of the Lords in Parliament, by which the Earle of Dumfermlin and Lord Lowdon onely were authoriſed to come and preſent their juſtification to Us, and they could for the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1140:24"/>preſent have no other, the Parliament now not ſitting. Whereupon Wee adviſing ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with the Committee what were beſt to bee done in this weighty buſineſſe, and conſidering that if they ſhould bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed without further hearing, they would take occaſion to clamour: Although Wee held Our Selfe bound neither in Honour nor Juſtice to heare them any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they having offered no foundation for an accommodation, nor having power to doe it; yet to the end that no colour of ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter conſtruction might be left, and that Wee might juſtifie Our Selfe to God and the World, that Wee have omitted nothing on Our part that might tend to peace, and to the ſettling of a better intelligence between Us and them, Wee did reſolve, that Wee would continue to heare them, and make Our objections to ſuch particulars as had been propoſed in Parliament; and againſt which Wee had juſt ground of exception, that ſo it might appeare, whether they could give Us that ſatisfaction which they promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and preſumed.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:1140:25"/>
            <p>This Wee having declared to them, not one of them made ſhew of the leaſt ſenſe of this Our grace and goodneſſe ſo expreſſed to them; which the Lord Marqueſſe Hammil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun obſerving, tooke occaſion of himſelfe to ſay, that though hee were not of their companie, yet being a Scottiſhman, hee held himſelfe obliged to acknowledge with all humility this Our ſingular and Princely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to his Countrie, and beſought Us to accept his moſt humble thankes for it. This drew them to do the like, and ſo they preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their humble thanks to Us on their knees.</p>
            <p>At the next meeting of the Committee, the ſaid Petitioners produced the paper above-mentioned, ſubſcribed by ſome of the Lords remaining at Edinburgh, as aforeſaid, by which the Earle of Dumfermlin and Lord Lowdon onely were heretofore au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed to come and preſent their juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Us; which paper being read, the whole Committee agreed that the Petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners had no power by this paper, no more then by the former, to give Us any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to oblige thoſe from whom they
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1140:25"/>came, but onely to endeavour to juſtifie themſelves, and the former proceedings of the Parliament. Of all this Wee were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to give accompt to Our whole Councell of England, who unanimouſly concurred in opinion with the Committee, that the above-mentioned papers gave them no power at all. Nevertheleſſe Wee were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, according to Our promiſe, to heare them; and Wee did make objections to the moſt exorbitant of their demands: but their anſwers were very impertinent, and rather juſtifications of them, then any way ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory: Which could not be otherwiſe, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe demands were for the moſt part ſo contrary to Law and Monarchicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that they did anſwer themſelves, as by Our anſwers to them, formerly ſet downe, more particularly may appeare.</p>
            <p>Concerning Our promiſe of a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no man of ordinary ſenſe can imagine We ever intended it ſhould be ſo free, as not to bee limited with their owne conditions, ſubſcribed by the Lord Lowdon, which were to enjoy their Religion and Liberties,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1140:26"/>according to the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill lawes of that Our Kingdome; and if they paſſe thoſe bounds, as it is evident they have done, We remaine diſ-obliged, unleſſe they will have Us onely obliged, and themſelves left at all liberty to fly at Our Monarchicall government, without controll, to wreſt the Scepter out of Our hand, to rob Our Crown of the faireſt flowers belonging to it, and to deſtroy Our Regall power and authority, as manifeſtly they have endevoured to doe by their inſufferable intended Acts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, contrary to all law and reaſon.</p>
            <p>If it be further objected, that they aſſume this liberty by Our allowing of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and commanding Our former High Commiſsioner the Lord Marqueſſe of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miltoun, and other Our ſubjects, to ſubſcribe it; the anſwer is very ready, That there is a great difference between the Covenant and Band ſubſcribed by Our Commandment, and their Band; for that Covenant and Band was made by Our late Father King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory, <hi>Anno</hi> 1580. and obligeth thoſe that ſweare to it, that they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1140:26"/>ſhould mutually aſsiſt one another, as they ſhould be commanded by the King, or any authoriſed by him. But this new Band was made without Our conſent, and by it they ſweare mutually to aſsiſt one another, not excepting the King, which is indeed a meere cunning combination againſt the King. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, when any have beene required to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the Covenant, as the Lord Marqueſſe Hamiltoun was, and did, and in that ſenſe which he declared in print, the principall Heads of them did not onely refuſe it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but diſſwaded (as much as in them lay) all Our good ſubjects from ſubſcribing it, though the Covenant were all one with theirs, and ſo acknowledged by themſelves: whereby it doth evidently appeare, that it was not Religion they aimed to ſecure (as they pretended) for then they would have acquieſced with theſe Our commands, but meerely by adhering to their owne Band, to keepe Our Subjects in that condition, as they might be alwayes tied, and conceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obliged by Oath to take up Armes againſt Us whenſoever the time ſhould be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1140:27"/>fit for a totall Rebellion; which they have never left endevouring till they have brought to paſſe: ſo that by Our approbation of the old Covenant and Band, or by the ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Our Commiſsioner, they can have no ſolid foundation to juſtifie their now proceedings; and it will handly appeare that ever any Covenant was made in the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an world (except in caſes of Rebellion and Treaſon, as this is) where the Head was left out, or had not a negative voice.</p>
            <p>Neither can the Earle of Traquair Our High Commiſsioner his ſubſcription or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of the ſubſcribing of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, be any warrant for their rebellious courſes, ſeeing, as appeares by their owne Petition to him, they declare, that, <q>Now follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the laudable example of their Predeceſſors, they doe humbly ſupplicate for the ſame, and that they may bee allowed and warranted to ſubſcribe it:</q> which cleerely evinces, that what they did before, and of themſelves, without warrant of Authority, was neither laudable nor war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable: As alſo before the allowing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by the ſaid Earle of Traquair, it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1140:27"/>(as appeares by that which is prefixt to his ſubſcription) that it is one and the ſame Covenant with that of 1580. which, as appeares by the Reaſons heretofore dedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, will no way inferre any ground, or the leaſt ſhadow of reaſon for their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable combinations, or taking up of Arms againſt Us, or Our authority, or any deniall of Our negative voice.</p>
            <p>Now upon debate of this point at the Councell Boord, the Lords were of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that untill the Petitioners ſent from the Covenanters, would acknowledge that the Supreme Magiſtrate muſt have authority to call Aſſemblies, and to diſſolve them, and to have a negative voice in them, as is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed in all Supreme Powers of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they ought not to be heard.</p>
            <p>If they ſhall alledge (as they did when they came to the Committee) that their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands aforeſaid were but matters in <hi>fieri,</hi> and not abſolutely reſolved nor concluded, it is to be anſwered, That the impediment was not on their part that they were not concluded: Nay, the Lord Lowdon in his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1140:28"/>firſt ſpeech to Us at the Committee, did not onely juſtifie their proceedings in the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly and Parliament, as agreeable to the Articles of Pacification, and to the Lawes and practice of that Kingdome, but did deſire that We would ratifie and confirme thoſe their proceedings, and to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe command that the Parliament might proceed freely, and determine anent all thoſe Articles delivered in to them: Howſoever, good ſubjects ought to be wary how they come neere the ſuſpition of Rebellion or Treaſon, much more how they make De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that carry with them more then a ſuſpition of rebellious and treaſonable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, as theſe above-mentioned moſt manifeſtly doe.</p>
            <p>Now beſides the Inſolencies and Acts of Rebellion and Treaſon above-mentioned, committed before and in the Aſſembly and Parliament, Wee cannot but obſerve and publiſh to the world, that their carriage hath beene no leſſe exorbitant ſince the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſince the comming of their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioners hither, then before: for without
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1140:28"/>any Authority or Commiſsion from Us, they have taken upon them to levie and raiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſeverall parts of that Our Kingdome, in great numbers, which they have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exerciſed and trained, and have aſsigned them a Rendezvous, and a day to be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to march.</p>
            <p>They have made proviſions of great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Artillery, Munition, and Armes from forraine parts, which they have ready in Magazine to make uſe of againſt Us their Soveraigne.</p>
            <p>They have of themſelves laid taxes and impoſitions of ten markes in every hundred upon all and every Our Subjects according to their ſeverall Revenewes, to bee levied upon their Eſtates, for the maintenance of this Rebellion; and this they have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted with the greateſt rigour &amp; tyranny that can be imagined, howſoever they pretend the contribution to be voluntary.</p>
            <p>They have cauſed to be framed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, as well in Manuſcript as in Print, ſundry falſe, ſeditious, and ſcandalous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Pamphlets, concerning Our procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1140:29"/>with them; and amongſt others, one intituled, <hi>An Information from the Eſtates of the Kingdome of Scotland to the Kingdome of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi> which having come to Our knowledge, Wee cauſed it to bee read pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely at Our Councell Table, and the Lords in deteſtation thereof became humble ſuitors to Us, that it might be ſuppreſt by Proclamation, and burnt by the hand of the Hangman; which hath been done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>They have refuſed the Lord <hi>Estrick,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of Our Caſtle at Edinburgh, timber and other materialls neceſſary for reparation of the workes lately fallen downe there, notwithſtanding Our expreſſe commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Our Letters to them upon their Allegeance to furniſh him.</p>
            <p>They have committed ſundry outrages and violences upon the perſons of ſome of the Garriſon at Edinburgh, that came out of the Caſtle to buy victualls.</p>
            <p>They have begun to raiſe Workes and Fortifications againſt the ſaid Caſtle, thereby to blocke up that Our Royall Fort, and to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1140:29"/>render it unuſefull: And they have fortified ſundry other places in that Our Kingdome, and particularly <hi>Inchgarrie,</hi> where they have mounted divers Pieces of Ordnance.</p>
            <p>They have lately impriſoned the Earle of Southeske one of Our Privie Councell, and ſundry others of qualitie, for not adhering to them, and for their fidelity to Us.</p>
            <p>And whereas Wee have upon ſundry oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ſignified Our pleaſure to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of Edinburgh for the performance of ſuch things as have concerned Our ſervice, in ſtead of yeelding obedience, they have made anſwer, That they have delivered up the power of governing the Towne into the hands of the Committee of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Tables, by which they have not onely voluntarily diſabled themſelves to ſerve Us, but have incurred the guilt of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by conferring upon any that power of Government which they derive and hold from Us alone, and cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to any other without Our ſpeciall warrant and command.</p>
            <p>But to fill up the meaſure of their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1140:30"/>they have endeavoured to ſettle Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences in parts beyond the Seas, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to let in Forraine power into that Our Kingdome, as Wee are able to make appeare under the hands of ſome of the chiefeſt of them; as if the fire, which by their owne Rebellions they have already kindled within the bowells of that State, were not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to conſume it, unleſſe they added fuell to it from abroad. And herein appeares firſt their malignity to Us their naturall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne, in that they had rather proſtitute themſelves to a Forraine Government, and that ſuch as is different in Religion, then yeeld conformity to Ours: And then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly Wee cannot but take notice that the intereſts and ſafety of Our Selfe and this Our Kingdome of England, are highly concerned herein; For if a Stranger once take footing in thoſe Northerne parts, it is not hard to judge how eaſily hee may bee invited by ſuch guides as they, and ſuch an entrance as they will readily give him, to draw neerer to this warmer Climate of the South; and then how much the Engliſh
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1140:30"/>Nation are likely to bee beholding to their Scottiſh Neighbours for ſuch Inmates, is left to every true Engliſh heart ſadly to conſider, and in time to endeavour to prevent, leſt hee bee overtaken unawares by the miſchiefe which threatens every one in particular, and the whole Nation in generall; and yet all this with them is Religion and Lawes.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the World ſhall ſee that Wee charge them not but upon very good and ſure grounds, Wee have thought fit to ſet downe here their owne Letter: Of which We have given Our good Brother the French King accompt, being confident hee will not aſsiſt any Rebells againſt Us. The Letter followes, with this endorſement, <hi>Au Roy,</hi> which in France is alwaies underſtood from thoſe Subjects onely to their naturall Prince.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="fre">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIRE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Voſtre Majeſté (eſtant l'aſyle &amp; ſanctuaire des Princes &amp; Eſtats affligéz) nous avous trouv<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſaire d'envoyer ce Gentilhome le Sieur de <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> pour repreſenter a V.M. la candeur &amp; natueté tant de nos actions &amp; procedures, que de nos inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, leſquelles nous deſirons eſtre grave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es &amp;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1140:31"/>eſcrites à tout l'wuivers avec un ray du Soleil, auſſy bien qu' a V. M. Nous vous Supplions doncques treſhumblement (Sire) de luy adjouſter foy &amp; creance, &amp; a tout ce qu'il dira de nostre part, touchant nous &amp; nos affaires; eſtans treſaſſeurés (Sire) d'une aſsiſtance eſgale a Vostre clemence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couſtumeé cydevant, &amp; ſi ſouvent monſtrée a ceſte Nation, laquelle ne cedera la gloire à autre quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conque d'eſtre eternellement,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sire, de V.M. Les treſhumbles &amp; treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyſſants &amp; treſaffecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onnés ſerviteurs,</salute>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rothes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Montroſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leſlie.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mar.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Montgomery.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Loudoun.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Forreſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Engliſhed thus:</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Your Majeſtie being the refuge and fanctuary of afflicted Princes and States, wee have found it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1140:31"/>to ſend this Gentleman M. <hi>Colvil,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent unto Your Majeſtie the candor and ingenuity, as well of our actions and proceedings, as of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, which we deſire to be engraved and written to the whole World with a beame of the Sunne, as well as to Your Majeſtie. We therefore moſt humbly beſeech You (Sir) to give faith and credit to him, and to all that he ſhall ſay on our part, touching us and our affaires, being moſt aſſured (Sir) of an aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance equall to Your wonted clemencie heretofore, and ſo often ſhewed to this Nation, which will not yeeld the glorie to any other whatſoever to be eternally,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed> Your Majeſties moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate ſervants,
<list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rothes.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Montroſe.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Leſly.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Mar.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Montgomery.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Loudoun.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Forreſter.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now theſe affronts to Our Government, &amp; dangers to Our State, which have no rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all to Religion &amp; Law, but in the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1140:32"/>of them both, have neceſsitated Us to put the forces of this Our Realme in order, and Our Selfe into a condition to be able (by Gods help) to vindicate Our ſafety and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour againſt all thoſe, that under pretence of Religion and Law, have already riſen, or ſhall riſe up againſt Us, and to preſerve and keep in ſafety Our good and loyall Subjects, and to take care that the gangrene bee cut off before it ſpread too farre, to the endangering of this Our Kingdome of England. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe Wee profeſſe before God and all the World, that We never did, nor ever will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them from the enjoying of their Religion and Liberties, according to the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill Lawes of that Our Kingdome, and according to Our promiſe and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, ſubſcribed by themſelves at the Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but that We will governe them as a juſt and religious Prince: In aſſurance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if they will yet acknowledge their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer crimes &amp; exorbitancies, and in an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſubmiſsive manner, like penitent Delinquents, crave pardon for what is paſt, and yeeld obedience for the time to come, they ſhall ſtill find that Wee will bee more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1140:32"/>ſenſible of their Converſion, then Wee have been of their Rebellions; and that We rather deſire their Reformation, then their Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But if they perſiſt in their Rebellious courſes, and by that which they call the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of their Religion and Liberties accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Eccleſiaſticall and Civill Lawes of that Kingdome, will underſtand nothing but the trampling of Our Crown and Royal Authoritie under their feet, and the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſubvert all Lawes and Religion, as they have done hitherto by their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in the Aſſembly and Parliament, then We hold Our Self obliged, in diſcharge of that duty which We we to God; &amp; the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which he hath entruſted to Us, to have recourſe to Our coercive power, to prevent ſo many imminent dangers as threaten the publicke. This We take God to witneſſe We are neceſsitated to, and ſhall not undertake without extreme ſorrow and reluctation. Nevertheleſſe We truſt that God, whoſe Vicegerent We are, and by whom alone Kings reigne, being likewiſe a God of truth, and a ſevere puniſher of all falſhood and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, will no longer ſuffer his glory to be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1140:33"/>deſpiſed and profaned in Our perſon, by groſſe Hypocriſie, under the counterfeit habit of Religion, but will ariſe and ſcatter His and Our enemies. And for this noble Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Nation, whoſe glory it hath beene to have been governed many hundreds of yeers under a Monarchy, We doubt not but they will, as it becomes loyall and faithfull Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, continue their affection to Us and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall government, and not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be debauched and betrayed into an Anarchy, by ſuch as envie the happineſſe they have ſo long enjoyed, and the many glorious victories which they have atchieved, under Kingly government, but following the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lords of Our Councel and of Our Servants, will cheerefully aſsiſt Us in this Our juſt cauſe, wherein Our Honour and Safety, together with theirs, are ſo highly concerned.</p>
            <p>Our ſubjects in Ireland, by their late De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration in Parliament, have not only given Us a conſiderable ſupply toward Our preſent Preparations, to reduce Our diſaffected Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in Scotland to their due obedience, but have humbly offered Us their perſons and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1140:33"/>eſtates, even to the uttermoſt of their abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities for Our future ſupply, in a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary way, as Our great occaſions (ſhould that diſtemper continue) ſhall require. And this they deſire may be recorded as an Ordinance of Parliament, and that it may be publiſhed in print for a teſtimony to all the world, and to ſucceeding ages, of their loyalty and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Us, as it well deſerves. This is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular comfort to Us in the midſt of theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, and We have no cauſe to doubt but Our Subjects of England, who are neerer to the danger, will ſhew the like tenderneſſe of Our and their owne honour and ſafety, which will be no leſſe contentment to Us, and make Us, as a Father of Our people, take the ſame care of their preſervation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, that We ſhall of Our own. And this We aſſure them in the word of a Prince We ſhall ever doe.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
